<?stylesheet href="webdoc.dsl" type="text/dsssl">
<!doctype galandoc SYSTEM "galandoc.dtd">
<galandoc>

<meta>
  <title>gAlan User's Guide</title>
</meta>

<intro>
<p>
This is the user guide for gAlan version &galan-version;.
</p>
</intro>

<section heading="Introduction">

  <section heading="This document">

<p>
This document is intended to provide a reference manual for the gAlan
system. Currently the <link url="tutorial.html">tutorial</link>
provides a quick introduction to the actual workings of the
program. The user guide will probably sprout some extra chapters in
future, when I get a better feel for what topics need to be addressed.
</p>

<p>
<xref section="inst-conf"> covers installing (and compiling) the
system and making sure it runs as intended. <xref
section="plugin-reference"> provides a detailed reference to the use
and operation of the various plugins included with gAlan. <xref
section="motifs"> provides a quick look at some common patterns that
come up while working with gAlan.
</p>

  </section>

  <section heading="About gAlan">
<warning>
Please note that gAlan is still very much <emph>BETA</emph> software!
</warning>

<p>
gAlan is an audio-processing tool (both on-line and off-line) for X
windows (and, in future, Win32). It allows you to build synthesisers,
effects chains, mixers, sequencers, drum-machines etc. etc. in a
modular fashion by linking together icons representing primitive
audio-processing components.
</p>

<p>
Using gAlan is much like setting up an effects-chain for, say, a
guitar. You choose the effects units you wish to use, lay them out,
and then connect them to each other, starting with the guitar,
threading through the effects, and ending up at the amplifier (and
ultimately the speakers).
</p>

<p>
It's not just limited to acting as an effects-chain, though. You can
also configure it (using the same basic principles) to act as a mixer,
a sample-sequencer or drum machine, or a synthesiser capable of
emulating various analogue systems. The gAlan website has links to
some examples of sound produced by the system, and the <link
url="tutorial.html">tutorial</link> provides some descriptions of some
of the ways gAlan can be used. See also <xref section="motifs">.
</p>

<p>
gAlan was written by, and is copyright to, Tony Garnock-Jones
&lt;tonyg@kcbbs.gen.nz&gt;.
</p>

<p>
It was developed on <link url="http://www.linux.org/">Linux</link>
using <link url="http://www.troll.no/">Qt</link> v2.3, <link
url="http://www.gtk.org/">GLib</link>, <link
url="http://www.gnome.org/">ESD</link>, and <link
url="http://www.opensound.com/">the OSS sound drivers</link>, and is
released under the <emph><link url="http://www.gnu.org/">GNU</link>
<link url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.txt">General Public
License</link></emph> (but see <xref section="gpl-exception"> for an
exception regarding the plugins!).
</p>
  </section>

  <section heading="The gAlan Homepage">
<p>
gAlan is being developed out of <link
url="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</link>.  The main Internet
homepage for galan is therefore <link
url="http://galan.sourceforge.net/">http://galan.sourceforge.net/</link>.
</p>
  </section>

  <section heading="System requirements">

<warning>
You <emph>must</emph> use GCC 2.95.2 or 2.95.3 to build gAlan. Earlier
versions (and also RedHat's GCC 2.96) contain severe bugs in the C++
compiler. This means (unfortunately) that you will probably also need
to recompile Qt 2.3 if you're running RedHat 7.x, as the version
shipped as an RPM was compiled with GCC 2.96.
</warning>

<p>
In order to run gAlan, you will need:
<ul>
  <li>a working <emph>Linux</emph> system</li>
  <li><emph>GCC 2.95.2 or 2.95.3</emph> - Note that GCC 2.96 as
      shipped with RedHat Linux 7.x <emph>WILL NOT WORK!</emph></li>
  <li><emph>Qt 2.3</emph> or newer</li>
  <li><emph>GLib 1.2</emph> or newer</li>
  <li>Michael Pruett's <link url="http://www.68k.org/~michael/audiofile/">
      <emph>audiofile</emph></link> library</li>
  <li>a <emph>soundcard</emph> which can manage 16-bit stereo at 44100 Hz (full
      duplex is nice, too)</li>
  <li>a reasonably fast <emph>Pentium</emph> processor (this is not enforced - but
      a P166 or better is recommended. DSP is heavy going!)</li>
  <li>some <emph>patience</emph> while development progresses</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
Currently gAlan is known to build and run on these systems (err, this system):
<ul>
  <li>RedHat 7.2 using GCC 2.95.3</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
If you try compiling gAlan on a different system configuration, and
it's not on the list, please <link url="mailto:tonyg@kcbbs.gen.nz">let
me know about it</link> - including any special action you had to take
to get it running, any problems you couldn't surmount, and (if
everything compiled and ran OK for you), any problems you can see or
areas where gAlan could be improved.
</p>

<p>
Note that gAlan currently uses floating-point internally, so a
processor with an FPU is more-or-less mandated. Most 486s and all
Pentiums have an FPU.
</p>

<!--
<p>
The <b>Win32</b> support is still very much <b>alpha</b>. Please see the
README.w32 file in the source distribution and the <a
href="news.shtml">news page</a> for recent announcements regarding
Win32 support.
</p>
-->

<p>
gAlan currently only works with the OSS drivers on Linux - I haven't
tried <link url="http://www.alsa-project.org/">ALSA</link> recently,
but last time I did, the results were disappointing. Elliot Lee has
contributed basic ESounD (ESD) support - there are still a few
problems with latency, but that's more ESD's problem than gAlan's.
</p>

  </section>

  <section heading="Show me the code!" id="gpl-exception">

<p>
You can download gAlan from <link
url="http://galan.sourceforge.net/download.html">the main
website</link>. Full source-code distributions are available, and
occasionally a binary distribution is available.
</p>

<p>
gAlan is distributed under the GNU General Public License. <emph>As a
special exception</emph>, the plugins are <emph>not</emph> required to
be licensed under the GPL. The writer gets to choose a license for
each plugin he/she writes. So if any third party vendor wants to
distribute a plugin for gAlan with a different license, that's fine -
and if they're a little touchy about their source-code, they're
welcome to distribute the plugin as a binary only.
</p>

  </section>

  <section heading="How does it work?">

<p>
When you start the application, you are presented with a blank
sheet. You right-click on the sheet and a menu pops up, from which you
select the class of component you want to instantiate. You can link
components together by dragging from one connector-handle to
another. The handles on the top and bottom of each component are
<i>event</i> connectors, and the handles on the sides are <i>audio</i>
connectors, so events flow from the top of the screen to the bottom,
and audio flows from the left to the right.
</p>

<!-- %%% helpful picture of the mesh here -->

<p>
When you have the connections set up the way you want them, you
instruct some of the components you have placed on the sheet to
manifest their controls (by using the pop-up menu and choosing a
control from the "New Control" menu). The controls appear in a
separate window - the <i>control panel</i>. (You make the control
panel visible from the "Window" menu on the menu bar.) Drag the
controls around until they're laid out the way you want them.
</p>

<note>
There's a bug relating to dragging controls around the
control panel. See <xref section="faq">.
</note>

  </section>

  <section heading="Feedback">

<p>
I'd love to hear what people are doing with gAlan - if you use it, and
produce something interesting, I'd really enjoy hearing it!
</p>

<p>
Any improvements you can think of, or problems you can see, let me
know. I'll need constructive feedback to shape the software for the
next major release. Please check the main website before you email me,
just to check that your idea is not already known to me.
</p>

    <section heading="Contact Details" id="feedback">

<p>
If you'd like to contact me:
<ul>
  <li>send me email at <link url="mailto:tonyg@kcbbs.gen.nz">tonyg@kcbbs.gen.nz</link></li>
  <li>contact me via ICQ (tonyg, #25667961)</li>
  <li>contact me via IRC (I hang out sometimes in #jrandom on Undernet
      and <link url="irc://irc.openprojects.net/#jrandom">irc.openprojects.net</link>)</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>
If you need to talk to me (voice, I mean) then ask me for the number
via email. If you want to send me stuff, ask me for my mailing-address
the same way.
</p>

    </section>
    <section heading="New ports">

<p>
If you're building on a system not mentioned in the list of known-good
systems above, I'd like to hear about any problems you have, and
whether you make it to a running system in the end.
</p>

    </section>
    <section heading="New plugins">

<p>
If you develop a plugin for gAlan, I'd love to hear from you!  I'd
like to collect more plugins that I can either include with future
releases or link to from these pages for gAlan users to download.
</p>

    </section>
  </section>

</section>

<section heading="Installation and Configuration" id="inst-conf">

  <section heading="Installation and Compile-time Configuration">

<p>
Please see the various <code>README</code> and <code>INSTALL</code>
files included with the source distribution - installation and
compilation of the code is already covered in some detail there.
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="Runtime Configuration">

<p>
There are two environment variables gAlan listens to:
<code>GALAN_PLUGIN_DIR</code> and <code>HOME</code>. Both are used in
the search for plugins at startup time.
</p>

<p>
gAlan also has a <emph>preferences</emph> file. It's stored in
<code>~/.galan/prefs</code>.
</p>

    <section heading="Environment Variables">

<p>
Setting GALAN_PLUGIN_DIR to a directory name overrides the built-in
#define of <code>SITE_PKGLIB_DIR</code> for the case of searching for
plugins. (SITE_PKGLIB_DIR is still used to search for pixmaps. I'll
fix this eventually, when pixmaps become more important.) All the
files and directories under either the compiled-in default or the
value of GALAN_PLUGIN_DIR are searched for plugins.
</p>

<p>
The other place that is searched is the directory
<code>~/.galan/plugins</code> (aka $HOME/.galan/plugins). You can put
any plugins you personally want to experiment with here without
disrupting the installation on the rest of the system.
</p>

<p>
For further details about how plugins are found, you'd do best to go
straight to the source - the relevant file is
<code>src/plugin.c</code>.
</p>

    </section>
    <section heading="Preferences File">

<p>
This is a text file that is read in every time gAlan is started, and
<emph>written out every time gAlan exits</emph> - so don't put
comments or things that gAlan doesn't care about in there!
</p>

<p>
The format of the file is:
</p>

<pre>
option_1=value string
option_2=another value string
option_3=etcetera
</pre>

<p>
Order doesn't matter, but whitespace sometimes does. Basically, it's
best not to edit the preferences file by hand unless you really have
to - use the <emph>Edit/Preferences...</emph> menu option instead!
</p>

    </section>
  </section>

</section>

<section heading="Plugin Reference" id="plugin-reference">
<p>%%% To be filled in later.</p>
</section>

<section heading="Common Motifs in Mesh Design" id="motifs">

<p>
This section deals with themes that occur frequently when laying out a
gAlan mesh and describes how to build some useful subsystems of
interacting components. Eventually gAlan will support proper nesting
of worksheets, which will enable abstraction of these ideas into a
library of meshes, each of which can be inserted into another (like
subroutines in a programming language versus cut-and-paste
programming).
</p>

  <section heading="Multiple-voice Drum Machine">

<p>
This topic is covered by the <link url="tutorial.html">tutorial</link>.
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="Multiplexing many inputs">

<fig src="ug_motif01.png" alt="Illustration">

<p>
This image illustrates mixing many audio signals into a single audio
signal using a Gain component with its internal gain factor set to
1.0.
</p>

  </section>

<!--
<h4>Building an LFO (Low-frequency Oscillator)<hr></h4>
<p>
<div align="center"><img src="ug_motif02.png"></div><br>

This image illustrates an LFO attached to the cutoff parameter of a
low-pass filter. Note how an evtadd plugin is used to shift the
sine-wave from being centred about zero to being centred about one,
and then an evtmul plugin is used to scale the whole thing to the
depth of sweep that is desired (anywhere between, say, 250 and 3000
are useful factors). Note that the rate of the clock plugin determines
how often the cutoff frequency of the filter is updated - every time
the clock sends an event to the sig2evt plugin, the oscillator is read
and the result sent down the pipeline to the filter.
</p>

<h4>Building a tuned instrument from a sample<hr></h4>
<p>
<div align="center"><img src="ug_motif03.png"></div><br>

This image illustrates a Note Sequencer controlling the pitch and
triggering of a Sampled Voice. Note that the <b>right-hand</b> output
connector from the seqnote is used, because the <b>resample</b> plugin
expects a MIDI note. Sending a frequency to the resample plugin is not
possible - it expects either a resampling factor, or a MIDI note
(where it assumes that its input signal is tuned to middle C, C4, note
48).
</p>

<h4>Building an instrument from an oscillator<hr></h4>
<p>
<div align="center"><img src="ug_motif04.png"></div><br>

This image illustrates a Note Sequencer controlling the pitch and
triggering of a simple tone shaped by an ADSR volume envelope. Notice
that the output from the seqnote is used in two ways: twice as a
trigger (resetting the phase on the oscillator and triggering the ADSR
envelope) and once specifying the frequency of the tone to generate.
</p>

<h4>A more complicated oscillator-based instrument<hr></h4>
<p>
<div align="center"><img src="ug_motif05.png"></div><br>

Here we have taken the simple oscillator instrument from above, and
have added in an envelope-controlled filter. The signal from the
filter envelope is sampled periodically by a sig2evt converter, and
cascades through a multiplication <b>by the frequency of the note
itself</b> - this makes the filter cutoff frequency move proportional
to the frequency of the note - followed by a further multiplication
(so that the filter frequency is some constant factor <b>larger</b>
than the base note frequency) and an add, to make sure that the cutoff
frequency doesn't descend below a fixed floor value.
</p>

<p>
This is, in essence, an integration of the simple instruments above
with the LFO motif detailed further up.
</p>
-->

</section>

<section heading="Known bugs, and other problems">

<p>
The Win32 version is not very stable. This is in part due to the
underlying GTK+ libraries. The situation will slowly
improve. Code/patch contributions are always welcome!
</p>

<p>
Besides the Win32-specific problems, we have:
<ul>
  <li>Not enough bounds-checking is being done by the components. This
      can lead to SEGVs or FPU errors crashing the program.</li>
  <li>There are some problems with GTK+ (I think) which cause incorrect
      display updates in the control-panel.</li>
  <li>There are problems dragging controls about within the control-panel.
      Somehow the events aren't getting through to the correct widgets :-(</li>
</ul>
</p>

</section>

<section heading="FAQ" id="faq">

  <section heading="I like this program, and want to send you money! What should I do?">

<p>
This question gets asked a lot. Naturally, you should send me some
money (or interesting beer, or flash new hardware, or book vouchers,
or anything you like, really). You can find my contact details in
<xref section="feedback">.
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="I'm getting Gtk-CRITICAL errors and warnings when I run gAlan!">

<p>
If you're seeing messages like this:
</p>

<pre>
	Gtk-CRITICAL **: file gtkwindow.c: line 992: (gtk_window_realize):
	assertion !GTK_WIDGET_REALIZED (widget)' failed.
</pre>

<p>
then you are seeing something which is harmless, but which I don't
know how to fix. I've spent a couple of hours trying to get rid of
these messages, but with no luck. Perhaps a later version of GTK+ will
make them go away. Ignore them in the meantime, however. (Reported by
drkforce@berkeley)
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="Hey! There are no plugins listed under the New menu!">

<p>
gAlan needs to know where to look on your filesystem to find the
plugin files (which end in .so, on most systems). They are expected,
by default, to be in the directory <emph>&site-pkglib-dir;</emph>, and
must have both read and execute permissions set (<code>chmod
a+rx *.so</code>).
</p>

<p>
If you don't want to (or don't have the permissions to) put them
there, you can instead put them in a directory of your own choosing,
and set the environment variable <code>GALAN_PLUGIN_DIR</code> before
invoking gAlan, like this:
</p>

<pre>
	$ GALAN_PLUGIN_DIR=/my/dir/containing/all/the/plugins
	$ export GALAN_PLUGIN_DIR
	$ galan
</pre>

<p>
or the equivalent, if you're a c-shell user.
</p>

<p>
The other option is to place the plugins in the directory
.galan/plugins off your home directory, that is
</p>

<pre>
	$ cd &lt;wherever the distributed plugins are kept&gt;
	$ mkdir ~/.galan
	$ mkdir ~/.galan/plugins
	$ cp *.so ~/.galan/plugins
</pre>

<p>
If this problem occurs with the downloaded sources, after you've done
all three of <code>./configure</code>, <code>make</code>, and
<code>make install</code>, then I don't know what's gone wrong, and
you should contact the author. (Reported by Erwan Le Bras)
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="I'm having trouble dragging the controls around the control panel. What's going on?">

<p>
This is a known problem (see above). It's something I'm doing wrong
with regard to the flow of events that GDK is letting me see. I've
tried to fix it, and I'm stuck, for now. Any help anyone can give to
solve this one would be appreciated...
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="The controls in the control panel sometimes display incorrectly, or stop showing updates. How can I correct this?">

<p>
A workaround is to force the window to redisplay itself - you could
<ul>
  <li>iconise the window and then restore it</li>
  <li>drag the window off the edge of the desktop and back</li>
  <li>shade/unshade the window</li>
</ul>
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="gAlan sounds TERRIBLE when running on Win32. What's going wrong?">

<p>
Win32 audio output is a new feature (one day old, as of this
writing). It's currently just a very quick hack. There are some
problems with it, notably that the latency is enormous (about 400 ms!)
because I can't make Windows tell me that it's ready for more output
in time unless I use lots of double-buffering.
</p>

<p>
Anyone with Win32 audio output experience... I need some help with
it. It works (barely) but it could be much, much better. DirectSound,
perhaps?
</p>

<p>
<emph>Update:</emph> I've spoken with a friend of mine who did some
rudimentary profiling of gAlan on Win32 - and it turns out it is
spending an unacceptable amout of CPU time, (around 50%!) mostly I
assume in the mmsystem audio parts of the program. As WinAMP etc use
very little (~3%) CPU time, there has to be a good way around this.
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="The Win32 version of gAlan is missing features/keeps crashing/is buggy!">

<p>
This is most likely to do with the incomplete status of the port of
GTK+ to Win32. You can either wait until it gets a little better, or
help make it better yourself. Other possible sources of problems
include Windows' inherent instability and my primary development
platform being a Linux box.
</p>

<p>
Note that sometimes loading gAlan files created on an earlier
development version of gAlan will not load properly in more recent
versions. This affects both the Linux and Win32 builds of gAlan. I'm
working on making the file-loading code more robust.
</p>

  </section>
  <section heading="I've found a bug/I want a feature. What should I do?">

<p>
If you can fix it, or write it yourself, please, do so! (And then send
me the patch.) Otherwise, please check the documentation <emph>and the
web site</emph> to make sure it's not already known/being worked
on. If you are convinced you've really found a new bug, please send as
much information about the bug as you can gather (within reason) to
me, and I'll take a look.
</p>

<p>
I'm not going to guarantee I'll have time to work on improvements or
fixes to gAlan instantly, but I will try. I am a student and working
part-time to support myself, so my spare time can be somewhat limited.
</p>

  </section>

</section>

</galandoc>
